Translate and Rotate are two functions
Translate および Rotate の二つの関数は
that are commonly used to change the
ゲームオブジェクトの位置および回転を変更することが
position and rotation of a game object.
主な使用方法です。
In this example we begin by looking at
次のサンプルでは Translate からみてきます。
translate. You can see that the argument
Translate の引数は
of translate takes a vector3.
Vector3 型をとります。
So this example simply translates down
そのためこのサンプルでは Translate で
the Z axis, so you can see we've used 0
Z 軸を下向きに移動させるため
for X and Y,
X および Y には 0 を使用しています。
by 1 every frame because it's inside update.
これは Update の中にあることから 毎フレーム 1 づつ移動させます。
So let's see how that works. It's applied
では、どのような仕組みかをみていきます。
to our floorbot object.
今回は floorbot オブジェクトに適用されています。
And you can see that if I press play
もし Play を押下すると 毎フレームごとに And you can see that if I press play
it moves very quickly because it's updating
更新しているため、素早く移動することがわかります。
every frame. Now what we'd normally
通常、
do with a translate operation is to
Translate を用いて行うことは
multiply it by Time.DeltaTime.
Time.deltaTime に乗算することです。
This means that it will be moved in
これはつまり 毎フレームごとに 1 メートル移動するのではなく
metres per second rather than metres per frame.
毎秒ごとに 1 メートル移動するということです。
Then instead of specifically saying
それでは、明示的に
Vector3(0, 0, 1)
Vector3(0, 0, 1) とする前に、
we can use vector3.forward as a shortcut to this.
Vector3.Forward をショートカットとして使用することができます。
And we can then multiply by another value,
そして 別の値を、まったく別の変数として
which we can establish as a separate variable.
かけあわせることができます。
That way we can control it by using
これによりインスペクタ上の変数により
the variable inside the inspector.
制御することができます。
But what if we don't want this to happen
しかし、もし
every frame and we want it to be
毎フレームごとに発生するのでなく
based on a key press?
キー押下にもとづいて発生させたい場合はどうすればよいでしょうか。
Meaning that it only occurs when I press
具体的には 上向きの矢印を押した場合のみ
the up arrow?
発生させたい場合、はどうすればよいか、ということです。
Then I could do the exact same,
それができれば 下向き矢印の場合も
checking for the down arrow.
まったく同じことが出来ます。
This time I've used a negative value of
今回は負の値をもった Vector3.Forward の値を使用することで
vector3.forward in order to move
下向き矢印を押したときに
backwards when I press down.
後ろ向きに移動します。
Transform.rotate works in a very similar way.
Transform.rotate も同じような仕組みで動作します。
Again taking in a Vector3 into it's argument.
今回も、 Vector3 型が引数として必要です。
This time we're using the Vector3 shortcut
この場合は Vector3.up という Vector3 のショートカットを
Vector3.up.
使用します。
This represents the axis around which to turn.
これは どの軸を中心にまわるかを示します。
This is the first argument, and amount
それが最初の引数であり、次の引数は
to turn by is the second argument.
回転する移動量を示します。
Now we'll add in our variable called TurnSpeed
次に TurnSpeed と呼ばれる変数を追加して、
and when I press play
Play を押下すると
I can move the object around and
オブジェクトを動かして
rotate it using the left and right arrows.
左や右の矢印によって回転させることが出来ます。
And again because I've set these as
さらにこれらを public 変数としてセットしているため
public variables I can adjust them
スクリプトそのものを編集することなく
without having to go back to edit the scripts.
値の調整をすることが出来ます。
It should be noted that these functions work
これらの関数はワールド座標ではなくローカル座標で動作
on the local axis rather than in the world axis.
することを覚えておくべきです。
So where I'm using Vector3.forward
このため、 Vector3.forward または
or Vector3.up - this is relative to the
Vector3.up と指定した場合は
axis of the object it's applied to.
適用されているオブジェクトのローカル軸にそって回転します。
It's also notable that if you want
さらに覚えておくべきこととして
to move an object with a collider,
コライダつきのオブジェクトを移動する場合、
so something that's going to be interacting
つまり物理挙動と相互作用のある場合は
with physics - then you should not use
Translate または Rotate を使用すべきでは
translate or rotate.
ありません。
You should use the physics functions instead.
その代わりに Physics 関数を使用すべきです。
And you can see these in a separate lesson.
この使い方は別のセクションでみていきます。
The only time that you would want to effect
Transform に影響を与えてよいときというのは
transform is if you had a rigid body
Kinematic である Rigidbody である場合
that is kinematic.
だけです。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)